Welcome to lesson five and we'll be talking about ethics for data science and this corresponds to chapter 3 of the book. I've also
Just taught a six-week version of this course, I'm currently teaching an eight-week version of this course and will release
some some combination or subset of that as a
Fast AI and USF ethics for data science class if you want more detail
Coming in July. I am Rachel Thomas
I am the founding director of the center for applied data ethics at the University of San Francisco and also co-founder a fast day
I together with Jeremy Howard
my background
I have a PhD in math and
worked as a data scientist and software engineer in the tech industry and then have been working at USF and on fast AI for
The past four years now
So ethics issues are in the news
These these articles I think are all from this fall
kind of showing up at this this intersection of how
How technology is impacting our world in many kind of increasingly powerful ways
many of which really raised raised concerns
and I want to start by talking about three cases that I hope everyone working in technology knows about and is on the lookout for
So even if you only watch five minutes of this video, these are kind of the the three three cases
I want you to see and one is feedback loops and so feedback loops can occur whenever your model is
controlling the next round of data you get
So the data that's returned quickly becomes flawed by the software itself. And this this can show up in many places
One examples with recommendation systems and so recommendation systems are ostensibly about predicting what content the user will like
But they're also determining what content the user is even exposed to and helping determine what what has a chance of becoming popular
and so
YouTube has gotten a lot of a lot of attention about this
for kind of
Highly recommending many conspiracy theories many kind of very damaging conspiracy theories. There is also
They've kind of put together recommendations of paedophilia picked out of what we're kind of in a home movies
but when are kind of strung together ones that happen to have
young girls and bathing suits or
in their pajamas
So there's some really really concerning
Results and this is not something that any anybody intended and we'll talk about this more later
Um, I think particularly for many of us coming from a science background
we're often used to thinking of like oh
you know like we observe the data but really whenever you're building products that interact with the real world you're also
Kind of controlling what the data looks like
Second a second case study. I want everyone to know about it
comes from
Software that's used to determine poor people's health benefits
It's used in over half of the 50 states and the verge did an investigation on what happened when it was rolled out in
Arkansas and what happened is there was a bug and the software
implementation that incorrectly cut coverage for people with cerebral palsy or diabetes
Including Tammy Dobbs who's pictured here and was interviewed in the article
and so these are people that really needed this health care and it was a
roni
roni ously cut due to this bug and so they were really
and they couldn't get any sort of explanation and there was no appeals or recourse process in place and
Eventually, this all came out through a lengthy court case
But it's something where it caused a lot of a lot of suffering in the meantime
And so it's really important to implement systems with a way to identify and address
mistakes and to do that quickly in a way that hopefully minimizes damage because we all know software can have bugs our
Code can behave in unexpected ways and we need to be prepared for that. I
Wrote more about this idea in a post two years ago what HBR gets wrong about algorithms and bias
and
then third case study that everyone should know about so this is
Latanya Sweeney who's director of the data privacy lab at Harvard has a PhD in computer science and
She noticed several years ago that when you google her name you would get these ads saying Latanya, Sweeney
Arrested implying that she has a criminal record. She's the only Latanya Sweeney and has never been arrested
She paid $50 to the background check company and confirmed that she's never been arrested
She tried googling some other names and she noticed rigs an example Kristen Lindquist
Got much more neutral ads that just say we found Kristen Lindquist
Even though Kristen Lindquist has been arrested three times and so being a computer scientist. Dr
Sweeney to study this very systematically she looked at over 2,000 names and found that this pattern held in which
disproportionately African American names were getting these ads suggesting that the person had a criminal record regardless of whether they did and
traditionally a European American or white names were getting more neutral ads and
This problem of kind of bias in advertising shows up a ton
advertising is kind of the
Profit model for most of the major tech platforms and it kind of continues to pop up in high-impact ways
Just last year there was research showing how Facebook's ad system discriminates
Even when the person placing the ad is not trying to do so
so for instance the same housing ad exact same text if you change the
Photo between a white family and a black family. It's served two very different audiences
And so this is something that can really impact people when they're looking for housing when they're applying for jobs
And is a definite area of concern
So now I want to kind of step back and ask why why does this matter
And so a very kind of extreme extreme example, it's just that data collection has played a pivotal role in several genocides
including including the Holocaust and so this is a photo of
Adolf Hitler meeting with the CEO of IBM at the time. I think this photo was taken in 1937
an IBM
Continued to partner with the Nazis kind of long past when many other companies broke their ties
They produced computers that were used in concentration camps to code
other people were Jewish how they were executed and this is also
Different from now where you might sell somebody a computer and they never hear from them again
these machines require a lot of maintenance some kind of ongoing relationship with vendors to
Kind of upkeep and repair them and it's something that a Swiss judge ruled
It does not seem unreasonable to deduce that IBM's technical assistance
facilitated the task of the Nazis in the commission of their crimes against humanity acts also involving accountancy and
Classification by IBM machines and utilized and the concentration camps themselves. I'm told that they haven't gotten around to apologizing yet. Oh
I guess they've been busy. Terrible - yeah
Okay
Yeah, and so this is a very kind of a very sobering example
But I think it's important to keep in mind kind of what can go wrong and how technology can be used for for harm
For very very terrible harm
And so this just kind of
raises a question
questions that we all need to grapple with of how would you feel if you discovered that you had been part of a system that
Ended up hurting society. Would you would you even know would you be open to finding out?
Kind of how how things you had built may have been harmful
And how can you help make sure this doesn't happen. And so I think these are questions that we all all need to grapple with
It's also important to think about unintended consequences on how your tech could be
used or misused whether that's by harass sirs by authoritarian governments for propaganda or disinformation and
Then on a kind of a more concrete level you could even end up in jail
And so there was a Volkswagen engineer who got prison time
For his role in the diesel cheating case
so you remember this is where Volkswagen was cheating on emissions test and one of the kind of
Programmers that was a part of that
and that person was just following orders from what their boss told them to do, but that is not
Not a good excuse for for doing something that's unethical
And so something to be aware of
So ethics is the the discipline in dealing with what's good and bad it's a set of moral principles
It's not a set of answers
But it's kind of learning what sort of what sort of questions to ask and even how to weigh these decisions
And I'll say some more about
Kind of ethical foundations and different ethical philosophies later later on in this lesson
But first I'm going to kind of start with some some use cases
Ethics is not the same as religion laws social norms or feelings. Although it does have overlap with all these things
It's not a fixed set of rules
It's well founded standards are right and wrong and this is something we're
Clearly not everybody agrees on the ethical action in in every case
But that doesn't mean that kind of anything goes or that all actions are considered
Equally ethical there are many things that are widely agreed upon
and there are kind of a
philosophically
Safa chol underpinnings for kind of making these decisions and I think this is also the ongoing study and development of our ethical standards
It's a kind of never-ending process of learning to
kind of
practice our ethical wisdom
And I'm gonna refer it several times to so here
I'm referring to a few articles from the Markkula Center for tech X at Santa Clara University
In particular the work of Shannon valour Brian Greene and arena Ray COO who is fantastic and they have a lot of resources
Some of which I'll circle back to later
Later in this talk. I spent years of my life studying ethics. It was my major at University and
How much time on the question of what is ethics?
I think I'll take away from that is studying the philosophy ethics was not particularly helpful in
Learning about ethics. Yes, and I will try to keep this kind of very very applied and very practical
Also, very kind of tech industry-specific of what what do you need in terms of applied ethics? Mykola said it's great
They somehow they take stuff that I thought was super dry and turn it into
useful checklists and things I
Did want to note this was really neat
so Casey fees lawyers a professor at University of Colorado that I really admire and
She created a crowd-sourced spreadsheet of tech ethics syllabi
This was maybe two years ago and got over 200
syllabi entered into this this crowd-sourced spreadsheet and then she did a
meta-analysis on them of kind of looking at all sorts of aspects of the syllabi and what's being taught and how it's being taught and
And published a paper on it. What do we teach when we teach technics and a few interesting things about it?
Is it raises there a lot of?
ongoing discussions and lack of agreement on how to how to best teach technics
Should it be a standalone course versus worked into every course in the curriculum?
who should teach it a computer scientist a philosopher a sociologist and
And she analyzed for the syllabi
What was the course home in the instructor home? And you can see that the the instructors came from a range of courses?
including computer a range of disciplines computer science information science philosophy
science and tech studies engineering law math business
What topics to cover a huge range of topics that can be covered?
Including a law and policy privacy and surveillance in equality justice and human rights
Environmental impact AI and robots and professional ethics work in labor cybersecurity
The list goes on and on and so this is clearly more than can be covered in any even a full semester
length course and certainly not in a
kind of a single single lecture
What learning outcomes this is an area where there's a little bit more
Agreement, we're kind of the number one skill that courses were trying to teach was critique
followed by spotting issues making arguments and so a lot of this is just even learning to spot what the issues are and how to
critically evaluate
Kind of a piece of technology or a design proposal to see you know, what could go wrong what the the risks could be
All right
So so we're gonna go through kind of a few different
Core topics and as I suggested this is gonna be a kind of extreme subset of what could be covered
I was trying to pick things that we think are
very important and high-impact
So one is read course and accountability
so I already shared this example earlier of
You know the system that just determining poor people's healthcare benefits having a bug
And something that was kind of terrible about this. Nobody took responsibility even once the bug was found
so the creator of the algorithm was interviewed and
Asked they asked him
you know should people be able to get an explanation for why their benefits have been cut and he gave this very callous answer of
You know
Yeah, they probably should but I should probably dust under my bed, you know
Like who's gonna do that which is very callous and then he ended up blaming the policymakers
For how they had rolled out the algorithm
the policymakers
You know could blame the software engineers that implemented it and so there was a lot of passing the buck here
Dana Boyd has said that
You know, it's always been a challenge for
Bureaucracy to assign responsibility or bureaucracy is used to evade responsibility
and today's algorithmic systems are often extending bureaucracy a
Couple of questions and comments about
Cultural context yeah of any notes that they didn't seem to be any mention of cultural contexts for ethics as part of those
Syllabi, and somebody else was asking
How do you deal you know is this culturally dependent? And how do you deal with that? And it is culturally dependent?
I will mention this briefly later on so I'm gonna share
three different ethical philosophies that are kind of from the west and we'll talk just
Briefly have one slide on for instance right now
There are a number of indigenous data sovereignty movements. And I know the Maori data sovereignty movement has been particularly active
But different, you know different cultures do have different views on ethics. And I think that the cultural context is incredibly important
And we will not get into it tonight
But there's also kind of a growing field of algorithmic colonialism and kind of studying. What are some of the issues when you have
Technologies built in one, you know particular country and culture being implemented, you know
Halfway across the world in very different cultural context often with little to no input from people
people living in that culture and
Although I do want to say that there are
things that are
Widely, although not universally agreed on and so for instance the Universal Declaration on human rights despite the name it is not
Universally accepted but many many different countries have accepted that as a human rights framework and as those being fundamental rights
and so there are kind of
principles that are often held cross culturally although
Yeah, it's rare for something probably to be truly truly universal
So returning to this topic of kind of accountability in recourse
Keep in mind is the data contains heirs. And so there was a dank database used in California
It's tracking supposedly gang members and an auditor found that there were 42
babies under the age of 1 who had been entered into this database and
Something concerning about the database is that it's basically never updated
I mean people are added but they're not removed and so once you're in there you're in there and
And 28 of those babies were marked as having admitted to being gang members
and so keep in mind that this is just a really obvious example of the air, but how many other kind of
Totally wrong entries are there
another example of data containing errors involves the
the three credit bureaus in the United States
the FTC's large-scale study of credit reports found that 26% had at least one mistake in their files and
5% had errors that could be devastating. I'm gonna this is the headline of an article that was written by a
public radio reporter who went to get a an apartment and the landlord called him back afterwards and said
You know your background check showed up that you had firearms
convictions and
This person did not have any firearms convictions and it's something where in most cases the landlord would probably not even tell
Tell you and let you know, that's why you weren't getting the apartment. And so
and
This guy looked into it
I should note that this guy was white, which I'm sure helped him in getting the benefit of the doubt and
found this ere and
He made
Dozens of calls and could not get it fixed
Until he told them that he was a reporter and that he was going to be writing about it
Which is something that most of us would not be able to do
But it was even once he had pinpointed the air and he had to you know, talk to
The you know like County Clerk and the place he used to live
It was still a very difficult process to get it updated and this can have a huge huge impact on people's lives
There's also the issue of when technology is used in ways that the creators may not have intended
so for instance with facial recognition
It is pretty much entirely being developed for adults yet
NYPD is putting the photos of children as young as age 11 into into databases
And we know the error rates are higher. This is not how it was developed
So this is this is a serious serious concern
And there are a number of kind of misuses the Georgetown Center for privacy and Technology, which is fantastic
You should definitely be following them
Did a report garbage in garbage out looking at how police we're using facial recognition and practice and they found some really concerning
examples for instance in one case NYPD
had a photo of a suspect and they
Wasn't returning any matches and they said well this person kind of looks like Woody Harrelson
so then they googled the actor Woody Harrelson and put his face into the
Facial recognition and use that to generate leads
And this is clearly not the correct you said all but it's it's a way that it's being it's being used
And so there's kind of total lack of accountability here
And then another kind of study of cases in all 50 states of
police officers kind of abusing confidential databases to look up X romantic partners or to look up
activists and so
You know here this is not necessarily an and the data, although that can be present as well
But kind of keeping in mind how it can be misused by the users
All right
the next topic is feedback loops and metrics and so I talked a bit about feedback loops in the beginning is kind of one of
one of the three
key use cases
And so this is a topic. I wrote a blog post about this fall
The problem with metrics is a big problem for AI and then together with David you Minsky who's director of the data Institute
Expanded this into a paper
Reliance on metrics is a fundamental challenge for AI and this was accepted to the ethics and data science conference
but over emphasizing metrics can lead to a number of problems including
manipulation gaming
myopic focus on short-term goals because it's easier to
track short-term quantities
unexpected negative consequences and
Much of AI and machine learning centers on optimizing a metric
This is kind of both, you know, the strength of machine learning is it's gotten really really good at optimizing metrics
But I think this is also kind of inherently a weakness or a limitation
I'm going to give a few examples and this can happen even not just in machine learning
kind of but in
analog
Examples as well
So this is from a study of when English is England's public health system
implemented a lot more targets
Around numbers in the early 2000s and the study was called. What's what's measured is what matters?
And so they found so one of the targets was around reducing ER wait times, which seems like a good goal
however, this led to
cancelling scheduled operations to draft extra staff into the ER
So if they felt like there were too many people that you are they were just start canceling operations so they could get more doctors
Requiring patients to wait in queues of ambulances because time waiting an ambulance didn't count towards your your er wait time
Turning stretchers into beds by putting them in hallways
I mean, there are also big discrepancies in the numbers reported by hospitals versus by patients
And so if you ask the hospital on average how long people waiting
You get a very different answer than when you're asking the patients. How long did you have to wait?
Another another example is
of SAE grading software
And so this essay grading software I believe is being used in 22 states now in the United States
Yes, 20 states and it tends to focus on metrics like sentence length vocabulary spelling subject verb agreement because these are the things
that we we know how to measure and how to measure with a computer but I can't evaluate things like creativity or
novelty
However, gibberish essays with lots of sophisticated words score well, and there are even examples of people
Creating computer programs to generate these kind of gibberish sophisticated essays and then there
you know graded by this other computer program and highly rated and
There's also bias in this essays by
african-american students received lower grades from the computer than from expert human graders and
essays by students from mainland China received higher scores from the computer than from expert human graders and
authors of the study thought that they this this results suggest they may be using chunks of pre memorized text that score well,
And this is these are just kind of two examples
I have a bunch more in the blog post and even more in the paper of
ways that metrics can invite manipulation and gaming whenever they're they're given a lot of emphasis and this is a
good hearts laws of
kind of a law that a lot of people talk about and it's this idea that the
More you rely on a metric the kind of the less reliable it becomes
So returning to this example of feedback loops and recommendation systems Guillaume has lot is a former
google, youtube engineer YouTube is owned by Google and
He wrote a really great plant post and he's done a ton to raise awareness about this issue and founded the nonprofit
I'll go transparency which kind of externally tries to monitor YouTube's recommendations
He's partnered with the Guardian and the Wall Street Journal to do investigations
But he wrote a post around how have been though in the earlier days
the recommendation system was designed to maximize watch time and
So and this is this is something else that's often going on with metrics. Is that
Any metric is just a proxy for what you truly care about. And so
Here, you know the team at Google was saying well, you know, if you're watching more YouTube it signals to to us that they're happier
however, this also ends up incentivizing content that tells you the rest of the media is lying because
Kind of believing that everybody else is lying. We'll encourage you to spend more time on a particular platform
So Gilmer at a great post about this
Kind of mechanism that's at play and you know, this is not just YouTube. This is any recommendation system. Could I think be
Susceptible to this and there have been a lot of talk about kind of issues with many recommendation systems across platforms
But it is it is something to be mindful of and something that the kind of creators of this did not anticipate
And
last year
um kind of gathered this data on
So here the x-axis is the number of channels
Number of YouTube channels recommending a video and the y-axis is the log of the views and we see this extreme outlier
Which was Russia's today take Russia. Today's take on the Mueller report, and this is something that
Guillaume observed and then was picked up by the the Washington Post. But this this strongly suggests that Russia today has perhaps gamed the the
Recommendation algorithm which is which is not surprising and it's something that I think many content creators are
conscious of and trying to you know experiment and see what what gets more heavily recommended and thus more views so
it's important to note that our online environments are designed to be addictive and so
when kind of what we click on is often used as a proxy of of
What we enjoy or what we like that's not necessarily though four of our kind of like our best selves or our higher selves
It's you know, it's what we're clicking on in this kind of highly
addictive
environment that's often appealing to
Some of our kind of lower instincts saying up to effect. She uses the analogy of a cafeteria. That's kind of shoving salty sugary
Fatty foods in our faces and then learning that hey people really like salty sugary fatty foods
Which I think most of us do in a kind of very primal way, but we often you know
kind of our higher self is like oh
I don't want to be eating junk food all the time and online we often kind of don't have a
great mechanisms to say, you know like oh I
Really want to read like more long-form articles that took months to research and are gonna take a long time to digest
While we may want to do that our online environments or not. I'm not always conducive to it
Yes ceramic their comment about the false sense of security argument, which is very relevant
Hoff's, did you have anything to say about its false sense of security?
Can you say more
There's a
Common feedback at the moment that people
Don't wear masks because they're my little sense of security
That kind of makes sense to you
I don't think that's a good argument at all
In general
There's so many other people including Jeremy have pointed this out. There's so many
actions we take to make our lives safer whether that's wearing seatbelts or wearing helmets when biking and
Practicing safe sex like all sorts of things where we really want to
Maximize our safety and so I think is a net effect. You had a great thread on this today of
It's not that there can never be any sort of impact in which people have a false sense of security
But it is something that you would really want to be gathering data on and build a strong case around and not just assume
It's gonna happen
and that in
Most cases people can think of even if that is a small second-order?
Effect the effect of doing something that increases safety tends to have a much larger impact on actually increasing safety
You have anything to add to that or
And yes
I mentioned before a lot of our incentives are focused on short term metrics long term things are much harder to measure
and often involve kind of complex relationships and
then the the fundamental business model of most of the tech companies is around manipulating people's behavior and
Monopolizing their time and these things I don't think an advertising is inherently bad
But they I think it can be negative when when taken to an extreme
There's a great essay by James grimmelman the platform is the message and he points out these platforms are structurally at war with themselves
The same characteristics that make outrageous and offensive content unacceptable are what make it go viral in the first place
and so there's this kind of real tension here in which
Often things. Yeah, that kind of can make content
really offensive or unacceptable to us are also
what are kind of fuelling their popularity and
Being promoted in many cases. I mean this is it
this is an interesting essay because he he just this like really in-depth dive on the
Tide pod challenge which was this meme around to eating Tide Pods, which are poisonous
Do not eat them and he really analyzes it though
it's a great look at meme culture, which is very common and how
kind of argues
there's probably no example of someone talking about the tide pot challenge that isn't partially ironic which is common in memes that even
Kind of whatever you're saying. They're kind of layers of irony and different groups are interpreting them
Differently and that even when you try to counteract them, you're still promoting them
So with the tide pot challenge a lot of like celebrities we're telling people don't eat Tide Pods
But that was also then kind of perpetuating the the popularity of this meme. So it's this is an essay
I would recommend I think it's pretty insightful
And so this is a we'll get to disinformation shortly
But the the major tech platforms
Often incentivize and promote disinformation and this is unintentional but it's it is somewhat built into their design and architecture
Their recommendation systems and ultimately their business models
And then on the on the topic of metrics I'm I just wonder bring up so there's this idea of
blitzscaling and the premise is that if a company grows big enough and fast enough profits will eventually follow
Um, it probably aura ties the speed over efficiency and risks potentially disastrous defeat and Tim O'Reilly wrote a really great article
Last year talking about many of the problems with this approach, which I would say is incredibly widespread
And is I would say the fund kind of fundamental model underlying a lot of venture capital
And in it though investors kind of end up anointing winners as opposed to market forces
It tends to lend itself towards creating monopolies and duopoly x'
it can
it's bad for founders and people end up kind of spreading themselves too thin so there are a number a number of
significant downsides to this
Why am I bringing this up in an ethics lesson?
When we were talking about metrics
But hockey hockey stick growth requires automation and a reliance on metrics
Also prioritizing speed above all else doesn't leave time to reflect on ethics
Um, and that is something that's hard that I think it you do often have to kind of pause to to think about ethics
and that
Following this model when you do have a problem
it's often going to show up on a huge scale if you've if you've scaled very quickly, so I think this isn't thing to
At least at least be aware of
So one person asks about
Is there a dichotomy between AI ethics which seems like a very first world problem and
Wars poverty environmental exploitation has been a problem I guess and
There's an answer here. Which something else. Maybe you can comment on whether you agree or I have anything to add which is that
AI X they're saying is very important also for other parts of the world particularly in areas with high cellphone usage
example many countries in Africa
Of high cell penetration people get their news from Facebook. And what's up in YouTube and though it's useful
It's been the source of many problems. Did you have any comments on?
Yes, I think the first question so AIX as I noted earlier
And I'm using the phrase data ethics here, but it's this very broad and it refers to a lot of things
I think if people are talking about the you know
In the future can computers achieve sentience and what are the ethics around that?
And that is not my focus at all
I'm very much focused on and this is our mission with the Center for Applied data ethics at the University of San Francisco
Is kind of how are people being harmed now? What are the most immediate harms?
and so in that sense, I don't think that
data, ethics has to be a
First-world or kind of futuristic issue. It's what's happening now
and yeah, and as the person said in a few examples, well one example, I'll get to later is definitely
the the genocide in Myanmar in which the
Muslim minority the ROC inga or
experiencing genocide
the UN has
ruled that Facebook played a determining role in that which is really
intense and terrible and so I think that's an example of
Technology. Yeah leading to very real harm now. They're also yeah whatsapp, which is owned by
owned by Facebook there have been issues with
People spreading disinformation and rumors, and it's led to several lynching
dozens of lynchings in India of people kind of spreading these false rumors of oh
There's a kidnapper coming around and in these kind of small remote villages and then a visitor or stranger shows up and gets killed
Whatsapp also played a very important role or bad role in the election of Wilson Aero and Brazil
election of to where today and the Philippines so
I think
technology is having a kind of very
Immediate impact on on people and that those are the types of ethical questions
I'm really interested in and that I hope I hope you are interested in as well
Do you have anything else to say about that or?
And I will I will talk about disinformation I realize those were kind of some disinformation
Focus and I'm gonna talk about bias first. I think it's biased than just information. Yes
Question when we talk about ethics how much of this is intentional unethical behavior?
I see a lot of the examples as ma graffiti competent behavior or bad modeling where the product her models rushed without sufficient
Nesting thought around bias so forth but not necessarily Maryland and yeah. No, I agree with that. I think that most of this is
unintentional I do think there's a Genoa well
We'll get into this some cases. I think that I
think in many cases the profit incentives are misaligned and I do think that when people are earning a lot of money it is very
hard to
consider actions that would reduce their profits
Even if they would prevent harm and increase kind of ethics
and so I think that you know, there's at some point where
Valuing profit over how people are being harmed is
You know, when does when does that become intentional is, you know a question to debate but I you know
I don't I don't think people are setting out to say like I want to cause a genocide or I want to help
authoritarian leader get elected and
Most people are not are not starting with that but I think sometimes it's a carelessness and a thoughtlessness
But that I I do think we are responsible for that
And we're responsible to kind of be more careful and more thoughtful and how we approach things
Alright so bias so biased I think is a an issue
That's probably gotten a lot of attention
Which is great and I want to get a little bit more in-depth because sometimes discussions on bias stay a bit superficial
There was a great paper by Hirini Suresh and John Guttag
Last year that looked at kind of came with this taxonomy of different types of bias and how they had
kind of different sources
the
machine learning kind of pipeline
And it was really helpful because you know different sources have different causes and they also require different different approaches for addressing then
The Hirini wrote a blog post version of the paper as well, which I love when researchers do that
I hope more of you if you're writing an academic paper also write the blogpost
Version and I'm just going to go through a few of these types
So one is representation bias
And so I would imagine many of you have heard of joy Balan wienies work
Which is rightly received a lot of publicity in gender shades. She internet gabru
investigated commercial computer vision products from Microsoft IBM and face plus plus and then joy Balan weenie and Deborah
She did a follow-up study that looked at Amazon and Karos and several other companies and the typical results
they kind of found basically everywhere was that these products performed significantly significantly worse on dark skinned women so they were kind of doing
worse on people with darker skin
Compared to lighter skinned worse on women than on men and then the kind of intersection of that dark skinned women had these very high
Error rates and so one example is IBM
their product was ninety-nine point seven percent accurate on light skinned men and
Only sixty-five percent accurate on dark skinned woman. And again, this is a commercial computer vision product that was released
question
It's a question from the Tremmel study group
Volkswagen example
In many cases its management that drives and rewards unethical behavior
What can an individual engineer do in a case like this especially in a place like Silicon Valley where people move companies so often?
Yeah, so I think I think that's a great point
Yeah, and that is an example where I would have I would have much rather seen people that were higher ranking
Doing jail time about this because I think that they were they were driving that and I think that yeah
it's great to remember that I
know many people in the world
Don't have this option, but I think for many of us working in tech particularly in Silicon Valley
To have a lot of options and often more options than we realize like I talked to people
frequently that feel trapped in their jobs
even though
You know
They're a software engineer in Silicon Valley and and so many companies are hiring
And so I think it is important to use that leverage
I think a lot of the kind of employee organizing movements are very promising and that can be useful but really trying to
kind of vet the the ethics of the company you're joining and also being willing to walk away if you if
If you're able to do so
That's a great great question
So what this example of representation bias here the
Kind of way to address this is to build a more representative data set
It's very important to keep consent in mind of the the people if you're using pictures of people
But joy Valentinian Tim net gabru did this as part of as part of gender shades?
However, this is a the fact that this was a problem not just for one company, but basically kind of every company they
Looked at
Was due to this underlying problem, which is that in machine learning bench benchmark data sets were on a lot of research
However, kind of several years ago all the kind of popular
Facial data sets were primarily of light skinned men. For instance. IG ba a
Kind of popular face dataset several years ago only 4% of the images were of dark-skinned women
Yes
Question I've been worried about covert 19 contact tracing and the erosion of privacy location tracking private surveillance
Companies, etc. What can we do to protect?
Digital rights post covert. Can we look to any examples in history of what to expect?
That is and that is a huge question and something I have been thinking about as well. I am I'm gonna
Put that off till later to talk about and that is something where in the course I teach I have an entire
Unit on privacy and surveillance, which I do not in tonight's lecture, but I can share some materials although I am already
Really even just like rethinking how I'm gonna teach privacy and surveillance in the age of covet 19
Compared to two months ago when I taught it the first time
but that is something I think about a lot and I will talk about later if we have time or
Or on the forums. If we if we don't that's a great question a very important question
On the topic and I will say and I have not had the time to look into them yet
I do know that there are groups that are working on what are kind of more privacy protecting
Approaches for for tracking and they're also groups putting out like if we are going to use some sort of
Tracking what are the safeguards that need to be in place to do it responsibly
Yes, I've been looking at that too
it does seem like this is a solvable problem with with technology not all of these problems are but
You can certainly store tracking history on somebody's cell phone
And then you could have something where you say
When you've been infected and at that point
You could tell people that they've been infected by sharing the location and obviously preserving away. I
Think some people are trying to work on that. I'm not sure. It's
Actually, technically a problem. So I think there's sometimes there are ways to
provide the minimum
and of level you
Know kind of application with it with whilst keeping privacy
yeah, and then II think it's very important to also have things of you know, clear like
Expiration date like we you know
like looking back at
911 in the United States that kind of a
assured in all these laws that were now kind of stuck with that have really eroded privacy of
Anything we do around Coppa 19 being very clear. We are just doing this for Coppa 19 and then
There's a time limit and expires and it's kind of for this clear purpose
And they're also issues though of you know, I mentioned earlier about data containing errors, you know
This has already been an issue and some of other countries that we're doing
Kind of more
surveillance focused approaches of you know, what about like when it's wrong and people are getting kind of
Quarantined and they don't even know why and for no reason and so to be mindful of those
But yeah, well, we'll talk more about this kind of later on
back to
back to bias
Yeah, we had kind of the the benchmarks
so in the benchmark that's you know widely used has bias then that is really kind of a
Replicated at scale and we're seeing this with image net as well, which is you know
Probably the most widely studied computer vision data set out there
Two-thirds of the image net images are from the West. So this pie chart shows that the
45% of the images in image net are from the United States
7% from Great Britain 6% from Italy 3% from Canada 3% from Australia
You know and we're covering a lot of a lot of this pie without having
having gotten to
outside the west and so then this has shown up in concrete ways of
Classifiers trained on image net. So one of the categories is bridegroom man getting married
There are a lot of you know cultural components to that and so they have you know much higher error rates on
on bridegroom's from
from the Middle East or from the global south
And there are there are people now kind of working to diversify these data sets
But it is quite dangerous that they can really be
Kind of widely built on its scale or have been widely built on its scale before these biases were recognized
Another key study is the compass recidivism algorithm, which is used in
Determining who?
Who has to pay bail? So in the u.s
A very large number of people are in president who have not even had a trial yet just because they're too poor to afford bail
As well as sentencing decisions and parole decisions
and ProPublica, I did a famous investigation in 2016 that I imagine many of you have heard of in which they
Found that the false positive rate for black defendants was nearly twice as high as for white defendants
so black defendants who were live from Dartmouth found that it was the
The software is no more accurate than Amazon Mechanical Turk workers. So random people on the internet
It's also the software is you know, this proprietary black box using over 130 inputs
And it's no more accurate than a linear classifier on three variables
Yet it's still in use and it's an use in many states
Wisconsin as one place where it was challenged yet. The Wisconsin Supreme Court upheld its use
if you're interested in the
kind of topic of how you define fairness because there is a lot of intricacy here and
I mean, I don't know anybody working on this who thinks that what compass is doing is his right?
But they're using this different different definition of fairness
Arvind Ron Yan has a fantastic tutorial 21 fairness definitions and their politics that I that I highly recommend
And
So, um going back to kind of this taxonomy if types of bias
This is an example of historical bias and historical bias is a fundamental structural issue
With the first step of the data generation process and it can exist even given perfect sampling and feature selection
So kind of with the the image classifier that was something where we could you know?
Go gather a more representative set of images and that would help address it that is not the case here. So
gathering kind of more data on
the US criminal justice system
It's all going to be biased because that's really kind of baked into baked into our history and our current state
And so this is I think good good to recognize
One thing that can be done to
try to at least mitigate this is
to to really talk to domain experts and by the people impacted and so a really positive example of this is a
Tutorial from the fairness accountability and transparency
Conference that Christian Lum who's the lead?
Statistician for the Human Rights data analysis group and now professor UPenn organized together with a former public defender
Elizabeth bender
Who's the staff attorney for New York's Legal Aid Society and Terence Wilkerson an innocent
man who was arrested and cannot afford bail and
Elizabeth and Terence were able to provide a lot of insight to how the criminal justice system works and practice which is often
Kind of very different from the you know more kind of clean logical
abstractions that computer scientists deal with but it's really
Important to understand those kind of intricacies of how this is going to be implemented and used in these
You know messy complicated real world systems
question
Out of the AI biases transferred from real life biases for instance
I like people being treated differently isn't everyday phenomenon and then -
That's correct, yes, and so this is often
yeah coming from from real-world biases and I'll come to this in a moment, but
Algorithmic systems can amplify those biases so they can make them even worse. But yeah, they are often being learned from from existing data. I
asked it because I guess I
often say this being raised as it's kind of a
reason not to worry about
Well, I'm gonna get to that in a moment actually
Think in two slides, so hold on to that question. I
Just wanna talk about one other type of bias first measurement bias. And so this was an interesting paper bias in deal
milena
'then and I had Obermeyer where they looked at historic
electronic health record data to try to determine what factors are most predictive of stroke and they said, you know
this could be useful like prioritizing patients at the ER and
So they found that the number one most predictive factor was prior stroke, which that makes sense
second was
Cardiovascular disease that's also that seems reasonable and then third most kind of still very predictive factor was accidental injury
followed by
Having a benign breast lump a colonoscopy or sinusitis. And so I'm not a medical doctor
But I can tell something weirds going on with
Factors three through six here. Like why would these things be?
Predictive of a stroke. Does anyone want to think about about why this might be?
I mean guesses you want to read Oh someone's yeah
Okay, the first answer was they test for it any time someone has stroke
Confirmation bias overfitting is because they happen to be in hospital already
Biased data eh I record these events
Because the data was taken before certain advances in medical science
These are these are all good guesses. Not not quite what I was looking for, but good good thinking
That's such a nice way of saying
So what that what the researchers say here is that
this was about
Their patients they're people that utilize health care a lot and people that don't and they call it kind of high utility versus low utility
Of health care and there are a lot of factors that go into this
I'm sure just who has health insurance and who can afford their co-pays there may be cultural factors
There may be racial and gender by there is racial and gender bias on how people are treated
So a lot of factors and basically
people that utilize health care a lot
they will go to a doctor when they have sinusitis and they will also go in when they're having a stroke and
people that do not utilize health care much are probably not going to go in possibly for either and
so
so what the authors write is that we haven't measured stroke which is you know region of the brain being denied a
Kind of new blood and you oxygen what we've measured is who had symptoms who went to the doctor received tests and then got this
diagnosis of stroke and you know
That seems like it might be a reasonable proxy for for who had a stroke but a proxy is you know
Never exactly what you wanted and in many cases that that gap ends up being
significant and so this is just one form that the measurement bias can take but I think it's something to really
Kind of be on the lookout for because it can be quite subtle
And so now starting to return to a point that was brought up earlier
Aren't aren't people biased. Yes. Yes, we are and so
there have been
Dozens and dozens if not hundreds of studies on this
But I'm just going to quote a few all of which are linked to in this
Sandy'll milena the New York Times article if you want to find find the studies, so this all comes from, you know, peer-reviewed research
but when doctors were shown identical files
They were much less likely to recommend a helpful cardiac procedure to black patients compared to white patients
And so that was you know, same file, but just changing the race of the patient
When bargaining for a used car black people were offered initial prices $700 higher and received fewer concessions
responding to apartment rental ads on Craigslist with a black name elicited fewer responses and with a white name an
All-white jury was 16 points more likely to convict a black defendant than a white one
But when a jury had just one black member it convicted both at the same rate
and so I share these to show that kind of no matter what type of data you're looking working on whether that is
Medical data or sales data or housing data or criminal justice data that it's very likely that there's there's bias in it
There's a question
No, it's gonna say I find that last one really interesting like this kind of idea that a single black member of the jury
Yes, it has some kind of like anchoring impact
I kind of suggests that oh, I'm sure you're going to talk about diversity later
but it's gonna keep this in mind that maybe like even
A tiny bit of diversity here just reminds people that there's a, you know, a range of different types of people and perspectives
No, that's it. That's a great point. Yeah
And so the the question that was kind of asked earlier is so why does algorithmic bias matter
like I have just shown you that humans are really biased - so
Why are why are we talking about algorithmic bias and people have brought this up kind of like what's what's the fuss about it?
and there I
Think algorithmic bias is a very significant worth talking about and I'm going to share four reasons
For that one is the machine learning can amplify bias
So it's not just encoding existing biases
But in some cases it's making them worse and there have been a few studies on this one
I like is from Maria de arteaga of CMU and
here they were they took people's I think job descriptions from LinkedIn and what they found is that
Imbalances ended up being pounded and so in the group of surgeons
Only 14% were women however in the true positives so they were trying to predict the the job title from the summary
Women were only 11% in the true positives. So this kind of imbalance has gotten worse
And basically there was kind of this asymmetry where the you know, the algorithm has learned it's safer
For for women to kind of not not guess surgeon
Another so this is one reason another reason that
Algorithmic bias is a concern is that algorithms are used very differently than human decision-makers in practice
and so people sometimes talk about them as though they are plug-and-play and are changeable of you know with
Humans this bias and the algorithm is you know, this bias. Why don't we just substitute it in?
However, your the the whole system around it ends up kind of being different and in practice
One one kind of aspect of this is people are more likely to assume algorithms are objective or error-free
Even if they're given the option of a human override and so if you give a person, you know
Even if you just say hey, I'm just giving the judge this recommendation
They don't have to follow it
If it's coming from a computer many people are gonna take that as objective in some cases
Also, there may be, you know pressure from their boss to you know, not disagree with the computer more times, you know
Nobody's gonna get fired by going with the computer recommendation
Algorithms are more likely to be implemented with no appeals process in place. And so we saw that earlier when we were talking about recourse
Algorithms are often used. It's scale. They can be replicating an identical bias at scale and
Algorithmic systems are cheap and all of these I think are interconnected. So in many cases, I think that
algorithmic systems are being implemented not because they produce better outcomes for everyone but has
They're kind of a cheaper way to do things at scale
You know offering a recourse process is more expensive being on the lookout for errors is more expensive. So this is kind of cost-cutting
Measures and Cathy O'Neil talks about many of these themes in her book weapons of mass destruction
Kind of under the idea that the the privileged a process by people the pourer process by algorithms. There's a question
Your questions. Hmm
This seems like an intensely deep topic aiding specialized
Expertise to avoid getting it wrong if you were building an ml product. Would you approach an academic institution?
Haitian on this you see a data product
Development triad becoming IDEO quartet involving an ethics or data privacy. Yes
So I think interdisciplinary work is very important I would I
Would definitely focus on trying to find kind of domain experts on whatever your particular domain is who understand the intricacies of that domain?
is important
And I think with yeok
With the academic it depends you do want to make sure you get someone who is kind of applied enough to
Kind of understand how how things are happening in an industry
But yeah, I think involving more people and people from more fields is is a good a good approach on the whole
Someone invents and publishes a better ml technique like attention or transformers and then next to graduate student demonstrates using it to improve
Facial recognition by 5% and then a small start-up publish
There's an app that does better facial recognition and then a government uses the app to study downtown walking patterns and endangered species and after
These successes for court-ordered monitoring and then a repressive government then takes that method to identify in this ethnicity and then you get a genocide
No one's made a huge ethical error at any incremental step yet. The result is horrific
I have no doubt that Amazon will soon serve up a personally customized price for each item that maximizes their profits
How can such ethical creep be addressed where the effect is remote for many small causes?
And it's all yeah, so that that's a great summary of how yeah, these things can happen somewhat incrementally
I'll talk about some tools to implement
It kind of towards the end of this lesson that hopefully can help us so some of it is
I think we do need to get better at kind of trying to think a few more steps ahead. Then we have been
You know in particular we've seen examples of people, you know
There was the study of how do I identify protesters in a crowd even when they had scarves or sunglasses their hats on?
You know and when the the researchers on that were questioned
They were like, oh it never even occurred to us that bad guys would use this, you know
We just thought it would be for finding bad people
And so I do think kind of everyone should be building their
Ability to think a few more steps ahead and part of this is like it's great to do this in teams. Preferably in diverse teams
Can help with that that process I mean on this question of computer vision there has been you know, just in the last few months
Is it Joe Redman?
creator of Yolo who has said that he's no longer working on computer vision just because he thinks the the
Misuse is so far outweigh the the positives
Intimidate gabru said she's she's considering that as well
So I think there are there are times where you have to consider
And then I think also really
Actively thinking about how to what safeguards do we need to put in place to kind of address the the misuses that are happening
Yes, I just wanted to say somebody really liked the Kathy O'Neil quote
Privileged are processed by people the poor processed by algorithms thing. They're looking forward to learning more reading more from Kathy O'Neal's head of
Yes. Yeah and in Kathy Anya also writes in the in Kathy O'Neill's a fellow fellow math PhD and
But she also has written a number of good articles
And it the book kind of goes through a number of those case studies of how algorithms are being used in different places
So kind of in in summary of
Humans are biased why do why are we making a fuss about algorithmic bias?
So one is we saw earlier machine learning can create feedback loops. So it's you know, it's not just
Kind of observing what's happening in the world? But it's also determining outcomes and it's kind of determining what future data is
Machine learning can amplify bias
Algorithms and humans are used very differently in practice and it'll also say technology is power and with that comes responsibility
and I think for all of us to have access to deep learning we're still in a kind of very
Fortunate and small percentage of the world that is able to use this technology right now
And I hope I hope we will all use it responsibly and really take our power
seriously
and I just I just noticed the time and I think we're about to start a
next section on on
analyzing or
Kind of steps steps we can take so this would be a good a good place to take a break. So
Let's meet back in
seven minutes at
7:45
>>>>>>>>>>>>>>>>>>>>>>>>>>>>>>>>>>>>>>>>>>>>>>>>>>>>>>>>>>>>>>>>>>>>>>>>>>>>>>> Hiromi
All right, let's start back up and actually I was at a slightly different place than I thought
But just a few
Questions that that you can ask about projects you're working on and I hope you will ask about projects you're working on
The first is should we should we even be doing this?
And considering that maybe there's some work that we shouldn't do
There's a paper when the implication is not to design technology
As engineers we often tend to respond to problems with you know
What can I make or build to address this but sometimes the answer is to not make or build anything?
One example of research that I think has a huge amount of downside and really no upside I see was
Kind of to identify the ethnicity particularly for people of ethnic minorities
And so there was work done identifying the Chinese we Gers which is the Muslim minority in western China
Which has since you know over a million people have been placed in internment camps
And I think this is a very very harmful harmful line of research.
I think that the
You know there have been at least two attempts of building
building a classifier to try to identify
someone's sexuality which is
it's
Probably just picking up on kind of stylistic differences
But this is something that a call could also be quite quite dangerous as in many countries. It's it's illegal
To be gay. Yes
<<<<<<<<<<<<<<<<<<<<<<<<<<<<<<<<<<<<<<<<<<<<<<<<<<<<<<<<<<<<<<<<<<<<<<<<<<<<<<<<<<<<<<<<<<<<<<<<<<<<<<<<<<<<<<<<<<<<<<<<<<<<<<<<<<<
So this is a question for me, which I don't know the answer to yeah
As that title says a standard scientist says he built the gate art
Using the lamest AI possible to prove the point and my understanding is that pointless to say
you know, I guess it's something like hey, you could use fast AI lesson 1
For an arrow too. You can build this thing. Anybody can do it
you know, how do you feel about this idea that there's a role to
Demonstrate what's readily available with the technology we have? Yeah, that's the thing that I think
So I appreciate that and I'll talk about this a little bit later open ai with GPT 2 I think was trying to raise a
raise a debate around
Around dual use and what is responsible release of of?
dual use
Technology and what's a kind of responsible way to raise?
Raise awareness of what is possible in the in the cases of researchers that have done this on the sexuality question?
to me
it hasn't seemed like they've put adequate thought into how they're conducting that and who they're collaborating with to ensure that it is something that
is
Leading to kind of helping address the problem
But I think you're right that I think there is probably some place for letting people ya know
What is probably widely available now? It reminds me a bit of my pen testing
Info? Yeah, where where
It's kind of considered it. Well, there's an ethical way that you can go about pointing out that it's fairly easy to be a
system
Yes. Yeah, I would I would agree with that that there there is an ethical way
But I think that's something that we as a community
Still have more work to do and even determining what that is
Other questions to consider are what biases in the data and something I should highlight is
People often ask me. You know, how can I
Devious my data or ensure that its bias free and that's not possible all data contains bias. And the
kind of most most important thing is just to
Understand kind of how your data set was created and what its limitations are so that you're not blindsided by that
But you're never going to fully remove it and some of the I think most promising
approaches in this area are
Work like timid Abreu's data sheets for data sets
Which is kind of going through and asking kind of a bunch of questions about how your data set was created
And for what purposes and how it's being moved maintained and you know
what are the risk in that just to really kind of be aware of of the context of your data and
The code and data be audited. I think particularly in the United States. We have a lot of issues with when private companies are
Creating software that's really impacting people through the criminal justice system, or hiring
and when these things are
You know kind of their proprietary black boxes that are protected in court
That's this creates a lot of kind of of issues of you know, what are what are our rights around that?
Looking at error rates for different subgroups is really important and that's what so kind of so powerful about
Joy, Balam wienies work if she had just looked at
Light-skinned versus dark skin and men versus women she wouldn't have identified
Just how poorly the algorithms were doing on dark-skinned women
What is the accuracy of a simple rule based alternative and this is something I think Jeremy talked about last week
Which is just kind of good good machine learning practice to have a baseline
but particularly in cases like the compass recidivism where this
Variable black box is not doing much better than a linear classifier
On three variables that race is kind of a question of why are why are we using this?
And then what processes are in place to handle appeals or mistakes because there will be errors in the data
There may be bugs and the implementation and we need to have a process for recourse
Yes
Can your explicit for me know?
Nobody voted them up at all
What's the thinking behind this idea that a simpler model
Is you gotta take a simpler model or other things being the same? You should pick the simpler one?
Is that what this baselines for what and if so, what's the kind of thinking behind that?
Well with the compass recidivism algorithm
Some of this for me is linked to the
Proprietary black box nature and so you're right if maybe if we had a way to introspect and what we're our rights around appealing something
But I would say yeah, like why use the more complex thing if the the simpler one works the same
And then how diverse is the team that built it and I'll talk more about team diversity later later in this lesson
Okay, Jeremy at the start, but I'm not the teacher
So it actually there's Jeremy do you think transfer learning makes this tougher?
Auditing the data that led to the initial model. I assume they mean Jeremy, please ask Rachel
No, they were they were asking you
That's that's a good question
Again, I think it's important
I would I would say I think it's important to have information probably on both datasets what the initial data set used was and
What the the data set you use to fine-tune it?
Do you have thoughts on that what she said
And then I'll see so while
Bias and fairness as well as accountability and transparency are important. They aren't everything
and so there's this great paper a mulching proposal by aw skis at all and
Here they talk about a system for turning the elderly into high nutrient slurry, so this is something that it's clearly an ethical but they
Proposed a way to do it that is fair and accountable and transparent and meets these qualifications
and so that kind of shows that some of the limitations of this framework as well as kind of being a good a
good technique for
kind of
inspecting whatever framework you are using of
Trying to find something that's clearly unethical that code that can meet meet the standards. You've put forth
That that technique I really like it it's like a it's my favorite technique from philosophy. It's this idea that you
You say okay given this premise?
Here's what it implies and then you try and find an implied
Result which intuitively is clearly
Saying and it's a really it's it's yeah, it's the number one
philosophical thinking tall I got out of university and I
sometimes we can have a lot of fun with it like this time to
Thank you
All right, so the next kind of big case study your topic I want to discuss is disinformation
So in 2016 in
Houston a group called heart of Texas posted about
protests outside an Islamic Center
And they told people to come armed another Facebook group
posted about a counter protest
to show up supporting freedom of religion and
inclusivity and so
there were kind of a lot of people present is this more people on the the side supporting freedom of religion and
A reporter though for the Houston Chronicle noticed something odd
which he was not able to get in touch with the organizers for either side and
It came out many months later that both sides had been organized by Russian trolls
And so this is something where you had
The people protesting were you know?
genuine Americans
kind of protesting their beliefs, but they were doing it in this way that had been kind of completely framed very
disingenuously
by by Russian operatives
And
So when thinking about disinformation it is not
people often think about
So-called fake news, you know and inspecting like a single post is this, you know
Is this true or false?
But really disinformation is often about orchestrated campaigns of manipulation and that it involves
Kind of all the seeds of truth kind of the best propaganda
Always involves kernels of truth at least it also involves kind of misleading
Context and and can can involve very kind of sincere sincere people that get good swept in it
a report came out this fall and investigation from Stanford's Internet Observatory where Rene arrests
and Alex Stamos work of
Russia's kind of most recent
disinformation or most recently identified disinformation campaign
And it was operating in six different countries in Africa
It often purported to be local news sources
It was multi-platform. They were encouraging people to join their whatsapp and telegram groups
and they were hiring local people's reporters and a lot a lot of the content was not
Not necessarily disinformation. It was stuff on culture and sports and local weather. I mean there was a lot of kind of very
pro-russia coverage
But that it covered a range of topics
and so this is kind of a very
Sophisticated phase of disinformation and in many cases it was hiring hiring locals kind of as reporters
to work for these sites
And I should say well I've just given two examples of Russia Russia - certainly does not have a monopoly on disinformation there are
plenty of
Plenty of people involved and producing it
Kind of on a topical
topical
Issue, there's been a lot of disinformation around
around coronavirus in kovat 19
I
In terms of kind of a personal level if you're looking for advice on spotting disinformation or to share with loved ones about this
Mike Caulfield is a great person to follow and he's even
So he tweets ed Holden and then he has started an info Demick blog specifically about the about kovat 19
but he he talks about his approach and how
People have been trained in schools for 12 years
Here's a text read it use your critical thinking skills to figure out what you think about it
But professional fact checkers do the opposite they get to a page and they immediately get off of it and look for kind of higher
higher quality sources to see if they can find confirmation and
Caulfield also really promotes the idea of
A lot of critical thinking techniques that have been taught
Take a long time. And you know, we're not going to spend 30 minutes evaluating each tweet that we see in our Twitter stream
It's better to give people an approach that they can do in 30 seconds that you know
It's not gonna be fail proof
If you're just doing something for 30 seconds
But it's better to to check than to have something that takes 30 minutes that you're just not going to do at all
So I wanted to kind of put this out there as a resource
I mean as a whole kind of set of lessons at lessons dot check, please see see and he's a he's a professor
And I in the
Data, ethics course I'm teaching right now. I made my first lesson the first half of which is kind of specifically about
Coronavirus disinformation I've made that available on YouTube. I've already shared it. And so I'll add a link on the forums
If you want if you want a lot more detail on on disinformation than just kind of this the short bit here
But so going back to kind of like what is disinformation?
It's important to think of it as an ecosystem again, it's not just a single post or a single news story that
You know, it's misleading or has false elements in it. But it's this really this broader ecosystem
Claire Wartell
first draft news, who is a
Leading expert on this and does a lot around kind of training journalists and how journalists can report responsibly
talks about the trumpet of amplification and this is where I
rumors or
Memes or things can start on 4chan and h han and then move to closed messaging groups
Such as whatsapp telegram Facebook messenger from there to community
concern reddit or YouTube then to kind of more mainstream social media and then
picked up by the professional media and
Politicians and so this can make it very hard to address that it is this kind of multi-platform in many cases
campaigns may be
Utilizing kind of the differing roles or loopholes between between the different platforms
And I think we've certainly are seeing more and more examples where it doesn't have to go through all these steps
But can can can jump jump forward
And online discussion is very very significant because people
It helps us form our opinions and then this is tough because I think most of us think of ourselves as pretty independent minded but
discussion really does you know we evolved as kind of social beings and to be
Influenced by by people in our in group and in opposition to people in our out group and so online discussion impacts us
people discuss all sorts of things online
here's a reddit discussion about whether the US should cut defense spending and
you have comments you're wrong and the defense budget is a good example of how badly the u.s. Spends money on the military and
Someone else says yeah, but that's already happening. There's a huge increase in the military budget the Pentagon budgets already increasing
I didn't mean to stop a sound like stop paying for the military
I'm not saying that we cannot pay the bills, but I think it would make sense to cut defense spending
Does anyone want to guess what subreddit this is from?
On popular opinion news changed my view net neutrality is
Heard good guesses but they're wrong. I love the way you say though
This is all from what it is. It's from the
Sub simulator gptt oh, so these comments are all
Written by GPT too, and this is in good fun. It was clearly labeled on the subreddit
That it's coming in GP g2 is a language model from open AI that was kind of in a
Trajectory of research that many many groups were on
And so it was released I guess about a year ago and
Should I read the unicorn story Jeremy, okay
So if many of you have probably have probably seen this so here and then this this was cherry-pick
But this is still very very impressive
So human written prompt was given to the language model in a shocking finding scientists discovered a herd of unicorns
living in a remote previously unexplored Valley in the Andes Mountains
Even more surprising to the researchers was the fact that the unicorn spoke perfect English and then the next part is all
Generated by the language model. So this is a deep learning model that produced this and the the computer model
Generated dr. Jorge Perez what appeared to be a natural fountain surrounded by two peaks of rock and silver snow?
Perez and the others then ventured further into the valley
By the time we reached the top of one peak the water looked blue with some crystals on tops at Perez
Perez and his friends were astonished to see the Unicorn heard
These creatures could be seen from the air without having to move too much to see them. They were so close
They could touch their horns
While examining these bizarre creatures the scientists discovered that the creatures also spoke some fairly regular English
Perez stated we can see for example that they have a common language something like a dialect or dialectic
And so I think this is really compelling prose to have been have been generated by a computer in this form
So we've also have seen advances in
computers generating pictures as specifically gans
so Katie Jones was listed on LinkedIn as a Russia and Eurasia fellow she was connected to
several people from mainstream Washington think tanks and
The Associated Press discovered that she is not a real person. This photo was generated by a gang
And so this, I think it's kind of scary when we start thinking about how
How compelling the text that's being generated is and combining that with
Pictures these photos are all from this person does not exist dot-com
generated by Ganz
and there's a very very
Real and eminent risk that online discussion will be swamped with fake manipulative agents
To have even greater extent than it than it already has and that this this can be used to influence public opinion
So
Oh, actually I guess it well no keep going
going back in time to
2017 the FCC was considering repealing net neutrality
And so they opened up for comments to see you know
How do Americans feel about net neutrality and this is a sample of many of the comments that were opposed to net neutrality?
They wanted to repeal it and included. I'll just read a few clips
Americans as opposed to Washington bureaucrats deserve to enjoy the services they desire
Individual citizens as opposed to Washington bureaucrats should be able to select whichever services they desire
People like me as opposed to so-called experts should be free to buy whatever products they choose
And these have been helpfully color-coded so you can kind of see a pattern that this was a bit of a Mad Libs
Where you had a few choices for green for the first?
noun and then in
Orange or red? I guess it's as opposed to or rather than
Orange we've got either Washington bureaucrats so-called experts the FCC and so on and
this
this analysis was done by Jeff Cao who's now a
Computational journalist at Pro Publica doing great work and he did this analysis
discovering this
this campaign in which
These comments were designed to look unique but had been created kind of through through some mail merge style
Kind of putting together
Mad libs. Yes
So this was this was great work by Jeff he found that
So while they received the FCC received over 22 million comments
Less than 4% of them were truly unique and this is this is not all malicious activity
You know, there are many kind of ways where you get a template to contact your legislator about something
But you know in the example kind of shown previously. These were designed to look like they were unique when they weren't
and
More than 99% of the truly unique comments wanted to keep net new to allottee
However, that was not not the case if you looked at the full the full 22 million comments
However, this was this was in 2017, which may not sound that long ago
but in in the field of natural language processing we've had like an entire kind of a
Revolution since then there's just been so much progress made and this would be I think virtually impossible to catch today
Using it, you know if someone was using a sophisticated language model to to generate comments
So chess asks a question, which I'm gonna treat it as a two-part question
I think it's not necessarily what happens when there's so much AI trolling
That most of what gets straight from the web is AI generated text
And then the second part and then what happens when you use that to generate more AI generated text
Yes for the first part. Yeah, this is a real risk or not risk
But kind of challenge we're facing of real humans can get drowned out when so much text
It's gonna it's gonna be AI trolling
and
And we're already seeing and ie in the interest of time
I have I can talk about disinformation for hours and I had to cut a lot of stuff out and but
Many people have talked about how kind of the the new form of censorship is about drowning people out
and so it's not necessarily kind of forbidding someone from saying something but just totally
totally just drowning them out with the
massive quantity of
Text and information and comments and AI can really facilitate that and so I do not have a good solution to that
in terms of AI
learning from AI
Text I mean, I think you're gonna get systems that are potentially kind of less and less relevant to
humans, and may have harmful effects if they're kind of being used to create software that is
interacting with or impacting humans, so that's a
Concern I mean one of the things I find fascinating about this is
We could get to a point where
99.99% of to it's and fast AI forum posts, whatever
Auto-generated particularly on kind of more like political type places where a lot of it's pretty low content pretty basic
And the thing is like if it was actually good
You wouldn't even know
so
What if I told you that seventy five percent of the people you're talking to on the forum right now?
I actually bots can tell which ones they are
How would you prove whether I'm right or wrong?
Yeah, I know name day. I think this is a real issue on Twitter
You know particularly
People you don't know of you know wondering like is this an actual person or a bot? I think it's a
common question people people wonder about
And can be hard to tell
But I think it has significance for
Has a lot of significance for kind of how human government works, you know
I think there's something about humans being in society and having norms and rules and mechanisms that
this can really
undermine and make difficult
And so when when gp2 2 came out Jeremy Howard co-founder of fast AI was quoted in
The Verge article on it
I've been trying to warn people about this for a while
We have the technology to totally fill Twitter Email in the web up with reasonable sounding
Context appropriate prose which would drown out all of their speech and be impossible to filter
So one kind of
step towards addressing this
Is the need for digital signatures or an Etsy on e?
the head of the Allen Institute on AI wrote about this in HBR
He wrote recent developments at AI point to an age where forgery of documents pictures audio recordings videos and online
Identities will occur with unprecedented ease AI is poised to make high fidelity forgery inexpensive and automated
Leading to potentially disastrous consequences for democracy security and society
and proposes kind of digital signatures as a means for authentication and
I will say here a kind of one of the one of the additional risk of kind of
All this forgery and fakes. Is that it also?
Undermines people speaking the truth and Zainab's fxg who does a lot of research on
Protests around the world and in different social movements has said that she's often
approached by kind of whistleblowers and dissidents who in many cases will risk their lives to try to
publicize like a wrongdoing or human rights violation only to have
Kind of bad actors say oh that picture was photoshopped
that was faked and
that it's kind of now this big issue for for whistleblowers and dissidents of how
How can they verify what they are saying and that kind of that need?
need for verification
And then someone you should definitely be following on this topic is Renee - Resta
And and she wrote a great article with Mike Godwin last year
Framing that we really need to think disinformation as as a cybersecurity problem, you know, it sees kind of coordinated campaigns of manipulation
And bad actors and there's I think some
Important work happening at Stanford as well on this
All right questions on disinformation
Okay, so uh next step at the coal foundations
so now
So the fast day I approach we always like to kind of ground everything and what are the real-world case studies before we get to?
Kind of the the theory underpinning it and I'm not going to go too deep on this at all. And
So if there is a fun article, what would an Avenger do and hat tip to Casey fees? Ler for suggesting this?
And it goes through kind of three common ethical philosophies
Utilitarianism and gives the example of iron man. I'm trying to max good
Deontological ethics of Captain America being an example of this adhering to the right and then virtue ethics Thor
Living by a code of honor and so I thought that was a nice reading. Yes
Where do you stand on the argument that social media companies are just
Neutral platforms and that problematic content is the entire responsibility if he uses just the same way that phone companies
Aren't held responsible when phones are used for scams or car companies held responsible when vehicles used to say terrorist attacks
And so I do not think that
The plot that the platforms are neutral because they make a number of
Design decisions and enforcement decisions around even kind of what their what their Terms of Service are and how those are
Enforced and that in keeping in mind
harassment can drive many people off of platforms and so
kind of
Many of those decisions is not that Oh, everybody gets to keep free. Speech when there's no enforcement. It's
Just changing kind of who who who is silenced
I do think that there are a lot of really difficult questions that are raised about this
Because I also I think that the the platform's
You know, it's they are they're not
Publishers, but they are in this I think kind of a intermediate
Area where they are performing many of the functions that
Publishers used to perform so, you know like a newspaper whiskey which is curating which which articles are in it
Which is not what platforms are doing, but they are
Getting closer closer to that
I mean I something I come back to is it is it is an uncomfortable amount of power
For for private companies to have yeah, and so it does raise a lot of difficult decisions
But I I do not believe that they are they are neutral
So, um for for this part I mentioned the markoulis Center earlier definitely check out their site ethics and technology practice
They have a lot of useful
Useful resources
And I'm gonna go through these relatively quickly as just kind of examples so they give some kind of deontological
questions that technologists could ask and so
Deontological ethics or where you kind of have various?
Kind of rights or duties that you might want to respect and this can include
principles like
privacy or autonomy
How might the dignity and autonomy of each stakeholder be impacted by this project
What considerations of trust and of justice or relevant?
This is some project involved any conflicting moral duties to others in some cases, you know, there'll be a kind of conflict between different
Different rights or duties you're considering and so this is this kind of an example and they have more
More in the reading of the types of questions you could be asking kind of when evaluating of just even how do you evaluate?
Kind of whether whether a project is ethical
Consequentialist questions
Who will be directly affected who will be indirectly affected?
Well, the end consequentialist includes
Utilitarianism as well as common good
Will the effects in aggregate create more good than harm and what types of good and harm?
Are you thinking about all the relevant types of harm and benefits including psychological?
political environmental moral cognitive emotional institutional cultural also looking at long term long term benefits and harms
And then who experiences them? Is this something where the risk of the harm are gonna fall disproportionately on the least powerful
Who's going to be the ones to accrue the benefits?
Have you considered dual use and so these are these they're again kind of questions
you could use when trying to trying to evaluate a project and
I think and the recommendation of the markoulis Center is that this is a
Great activity to kind of to be doing as a team and as a group
Yes, I
was gonna say like I can't I
Can't overstate how useful this tool is like it, you know, I think oh, it's just a list of questions
Yeah, you know but like this is kind of to me
This is that this is the big gun tool for for how you how you handle
This is like if somebody is helping you think about the right set of questions and then you let go through them with a diverse
Group of people and discuss the questions. I
Mean that's that. It's this is this is goal
like don't, you know go back and reread these and don't don't just skip over them because
Take them to work use them next time you're talking about a project. They're a really great
Great set of questions to use a great tool in your toolbox
yeah, and go to the original reading has even kind of more detail and
more elaboration on the questions
And then they kind of give a summary of five potential ethical lenses
The the rights approach which option in best respects the rights of all who have a stake
The justice approach which option treats people equally or proportionally and so these two are both a deontological
The utilitarian approach which option will produce the most good and do the least harm
the common good approach which option best serves the community as a whole not just some members and
so here three and four are both a
consequentialist and then
Virtue approach which option leads me to act as the sort of person I want to be and that can involve, you know particular
Virtues of you know, do you value trustworthiness or truth or courage?
And so I mean a great activity if this is something that you're studying or talking about it work with your teammates
The the Markkula Center has a number of case studies
That you can talk through and will even ask you to kind of evaluate them
you know evaluate them through these five lenses and how does that kind of impact your
your take on what the what the right thing to do is
It's kind of weird for a programmer or a computer program or data science in some way in some ways to like
think of these as tools like a steai your pants or whatever but I mean they absolutely are this is like
These like software tools for your brain, you know to help you you kind of go through a program that might help you
debug
your thinking
Great. Thank you. And
Then if someone brought up earlier, so that was a kind of very Western centric
intro to ethical philosophy there are other ethical lenses and other
Cultures and I've been doing some reading particularly on the the Maori worldview. I
Don't feel
Confident enough in my understanding that I could represent it, but it is very good to be mindful that yeah
there are other other ethical lenses out there and I do very much think that
You know the people being impacted by a
technology
like their their ethical lens is kind of what matters and that this is is a particular issue and we have so many kind of
multinational corporations
there's an interesting project going on in New Zealand now or the New Zealand government is kind of
Considering its AI approach and is at least ostensibly kind of wanting to wanting to include the Maori view on that
So that's a that's kind of a little a little bit of theory
But now I want to talk about some kind of practices you can implement in the workplace
Again, this is from the markoulis Center
So this is their ethics toolkit, which I particularly like and I'm just I'm not going to go through all of them
I'm just going to tell you a few of my favorites
So tool one is ethical risk sweeping and this I think is similar to the idea of kind of pen testing that
Jeremy mentioned earlier from security but to have
regularly-scheduled ethical risk sqweep's and
While no vulnerability
Vulnerabilities found is generally good news. That doesn't mean that it was a wasted effort and you keep doing it
Keep looking for for ethical risk. One moment
And then assume that you missed some risk in the initial project development
Also, you have to set up the incentives properly where you're rewarding team members for spotting new ethical risk
All right
Yet so got some comments here
So my comment here is about the learning rate finder and I'm not going to bother with the exact mathematical
Definition partly because I'm a terrible mathematician and partly because it doesn't matter but if you just remember, oh, sorry, that's actually not me
I am just reading something that
Patti Hendricks has trained a language model of me. So that was me greeting the language model of me
the real me
Thank you
This is a tool one. I would say another kind of example of this. I think it's like bread teaming of, you know, having a
team within your get sky and to find your vulnerabilities a
tool 3
Another one. I really like expanding the ethical circle
So whose interest desires skills experiences and values have we just assumed rather than actually consulted?
Who are all the stakeholders who will be directly affected?
And have we actually asked them what their interests are
Who might use this product that we didn't expect to use it or for purposes that we didn't initially intend and so then a great
implementation of this
comes from the University of Washington's Tech policy lab
did a
Project called diverse voices and it's neat they have both a
Academic paper on it and then they also kind of have like a guy
Lengthy guide on how you would implement this but the idea is how to kind of organize
expert panels
around
Around new technology and so they they did a few samples one
Was there considering augmented reality and they held expert panels with people with disabilities people who are formerly are currently incarcerated
And with women to cut their get their input and make sure that that was included
They did a second one on an autonomous vehicle
strategy document and organized expert panels with youth with people that don't drive cars and with extremely low-income people and
So I think this is a great guide if you're kind of unsure of how do you even go about?
setting something like this up to
expand your circle include include more people and get
Get perspectives that may be underrepresented by your employees
So I just want to let you know that this resource is out there
Tool six is think about the terrible people
And and this can be hard because I think we're often
you know thinking
Kind of positively or thinking about people like ourselves
who don't have terrible intentions, but really think about
Who might want to abuse steal misinterpret hacks Troy or weaponize? What we build?
Who will use it with alarming stupidity or rationality?
What rewards incentives openings has our design inadvertently created for those people?
And so kind of remembering back to the section on metrics
you know, how are people going to be trying to game or manipulate this and
How can how can we then remove those rewards or incentives? And so this is this is an important kind of important step to take
And
Then tool seven is closing the loop ethical feedback and iteration
remembering this is never a finished task and
identifying feedback channels that will give you kind of reliable data and
integrating this process with quality management and user support and
developing formal procedures and chains of
Responsibility for ethical iteration and this tool reminded me of a blog post by Alex Pierce that I really like
Alex fearest was previously the chief legal officer at medium and
Yeah, I guess this was a year ago
he interviewed or something like 15 or 20 people that have worked in trust in safety and
trust in safety includes content moderation, although it's not not solely content moderation and
Kind of one of the ideas that came up that I really liked was one of one of the people and so many of these
People have worked interest in safety for years at big-name companies
and one of them said the separation of product people in trust people worries me because in a world where product managers and
engineers and visionaries cared about the stuff it would be baked into how things get built if
Things stay this way that product and engineering our Mozart and everyone else is Alfred the butler. The big stuff is not going to change
And so I think at least two people in this kind of talk about this idea of needing to better integrate trust and safety
Which are often kind of on the front lines of seeing?
Abuse and misuse of a technology product integrating that more closely with product and ends
so that it can kind of be more directly incorporated and you can have a tighter feedback loop there about
What's going wrong? And and how how that can be designed against?
Okay, so those were these were well I
Link to a few blog posts and research I thought relevant but inspired by the mark Markkula centers tools
For protects and hopefully those are practices you could think about potentially implementing at your at your company
So next I want to get into a diversity, which I know came up earlier and so
Only 12% of machine learning researchers are women as this is kind of a very very dire statistic
There's also a kind of extreme lack of racial diversity and age diversity
and other factors
and this is this is significant a
Kind of positive example of what diversity can help with and a post Tracy Chow who was a
early early an engineer at Quora and later at Pinterest
Wrote that the first feature and so I think she was like one of the first five employees at Quora
The first feature I built when I worked at Quora was the block button
I was eager to work on the feature because I personally felt antagonized and abused on the site and she goes on to say that
If she hadn't been there, you know
they might not have added the the block button as soon and so that's kind of like a direct example of how
How having a diverse team can help?
Somebody kind of
kee-kee advice
for anyone wanting to increase diversity is to start at the opposite end of the pipeline from from where people talk about
The the work play I wrote a blog post
Five years ago if you think women and tack is just a pipeline problem. You haven't been paying attention
and this was the most popular thing I had ever written until
Jeremy and I wrote the the kovat 19 post last month of it. So the second most most popular thing I've written
But I linked to a ton of ton of research in there a key statistic to understand
is that 41% of women working in tack end up leaving the field compared to 17% of men and so this is something that
Recruiting more girls into in decoding or tack is not going to address this problem if they keep leaving at very high rates. I
Just had a little peek at the YouTube
Chat, and I see people are asking questions there
I just want to remind people that we are not
That grateful and I do not look at that. If you want to ask ask questions, you should use the
Forum thread and and if you see questions that you like then please put them up such as this one
How about an ethical issue bounty program just like the bug bounty programs that some companies have
No, I think that's a neat idea you have rewarding people for for finding ethical issues
And so the the reason that women are more likely to leave tech
Is and this was found in a meta-analysis of over 200 books white papers articles
Women leave the tech industry because they're treated unfairly underpaid less likely to be fast-tracked than their male colleagues and unable to advance
And and too often
Diversity efforts end up just focusing on white women, which is wrong
Interviews with 60 women of color who work in stem research found that 100 percent had experienced discrimination and their particular
Stereotypes buried by race and so it's very important to focus on women of color in in diversity efforts
as a kind of the top priority a
Study found that men's voices are
Perceived as more persuasive fact-based and logical than women's voices even when reading I denticles Scripps
Researchers found that women receive more of a feedback and personality criticism and performance evaluations
Whereas men are more likely to receive actionable advice tied to concrete business outcomes
When women receive mentorship is often advice on how they should change and gain more self-knowledge when men receive mentorship
It's public endorsement of their authority only one of these has been
Statistically linked to getting promoted. It's the public endorsement of authority and all these studies are linked to another post
I wrote called the real reason women quit tack and how to address it
that a question Jeremy or
Yeah, so if you're interested kind of a these two blog post I link to a ton of ton of relevant research on this
And I think this is kind of the the workplace is the the place to start in addressing these things
So another issue is tech interviews are terrible for everyone
So now kind of working one step back from people that are already in your in your workplace, but thinking about the interview process
And they wrote a post on how to make tech interviews a little less awful and
Went through a ton of research and I will I will say that the the interview problem I think is a hard one
I think it's very
time consuming and hard to to interview people well
But kind of the two most interesting pieces of research I came across one was from triple bite which is a
Recruiting company that
interviews
kind of does this first round technical interview for people and then
they interview it Y Combinator it's a Y Combinator company and they under review at my ax Combinator companies and they've this very
interesting data set where they've kind of given everybody the same technical interview and then they can see
Which companies people got offers from when they were, you know interviewing at many of the same?
companies and
The number one finding from their research. Is that the types of
Programmers that each company looks for often have little to do with what the company needs or does rather
they reflect company culture in the backgrounds of the founders and
This is something where they even they even gave the advice of if you're job hunting
look for try to look for companies where the founders have a similar background to you and that's something that while I
That makes sense that's going to be much easier for certain people to do than others and particularly given the the
Gender and racial disparities in VC funding that's gonna make a big difference
Yes
Actually, I would say that was the most common advice. I heard from feces when I became a founder in the Bay Area
was when recruiting focus on
getting people from your network and people that are
Like-minded and similar as possible. That was by far the most common advice that I heard
yeah, I mean this is
Controversial opinions, I I do feel like ultimately
like I get why people hire from their network and I think that long term
We all need to be developed. Well particularly white people need to be developing more diverse networks, and that's like a you know
Like ten year project. That's not something you can do right when you're
Hiring but really kind of developing
A diverse network of friends and trusted acquaintances a kind of over time
But yeah, thank you for that perspective to Jeremy
And then kind of the other study. I found really interesting
Was one where they they gave people
resumes and in one case
So one resume had more academic
Qualifications and then one had more practical experience and then they switched the gender one was a woman. When was a man?
Or you know male named a female name
And basically people were more likely to hire the male and then they would use a post-hoc justification of oh
Well, I chose him because he had more academic experience or I chose him because he had more practical experience
and that's something I think it's very human to use post hoc justifications, but it's a it's a real risk that
Definitely shows up in hiring
Ultimately AI or any other technology
I developed or implemented by companies for financial advantage ie more profit maybe the best way to incentivize ethnic open
is to tie financial or
Reputational risk to good behavior in some ways similar to how companies are now investing in cybersecurity because they don't want to be the next
Equifax
And grassroots campaigns help in better ethical behavior with regards to the use of AI. Oh
That's a good question. Yeah, and I think there are a lot of analogies with cybersecurity and I know that
For a long time I think was hard for people to make
Our people had trouble making the case to their bosses of why they should be investing in cybersecurity
Particularly because cybersecurity is you know, something like when it's working
Well, you don't notice it and so that can be can be hard to build the case
So I think that there there is a place for grassroots campaigns
And I'm gonna talk more I'm gonna talk about policy in a bit
It can be hard in in some of these cases where there
Are not necessarily meaningful alternatives
So I do think like monopolies can kind of a kind of make that harder that's it yeah a good good question
All right, so next step
Actually on this slide is the the need for policy. And so I'm gonna start with a
case study of
What what's one thing that gets companies to take action? And so
as I mentioned earlier a
investigator for the UN found that Facebook played a determining role in the ROE hanga genocide I
Think the best article I've read on this was by Timothy McLaughlin who did a super super in-depth dive
on
Facebook's role in Myanmar and
People people warned Facebook executives in 2013 and in 2014 and in 2015
How the platform was being used to spread hate speech and to incite violence one person in 2015
even told Facebook executives that
Facebook could play the same role in Myanmar that the radio broadcast played during the Rwandan genocide
and radio broadcasts played a very
terrible and kind of pivotal role in the Rwandan genocide
Somebody close to it
This said that's not 20/20 hindsight the scale of this problem was significant and it was already apparent and despite this in 2015
I believe Facebook only had four contractors who even spoke Burmese
the language of the of Myanmar
question
That's an interesting one
How do you think about our opportunity to correct biases in artificial systems versus the behaviors we see in humans?
Example a sentencing algorithm can be monitored and adjusted
This is a specific biased judge who remains in their role for a long time
I
Think I feel a bit hesitant about the it's it'll be easier to
correct bias in algorithms
because I feel like the
You still need people kind of making the decisions to
Prioritize that like it requires kind of an overhaul of the systems priorities, I think
It also
starts with the premise that there are people who can't be
Fired or disciplined or whatever I guess maybe for some judges that's true, but they're kind of maybe suggests that
judges shouldn't be
lifetime appointments
Yeah, even then I think you kind of need the the change of heart of the people advocating for the new system
Which I think can
Would be necessary another case kind of and that that's kind of the critical piece of getting the the people that are
Wanting to overhaul the values of a system
So returning to to this issue of
The Ginga genocide and this is a good kind of continuing continuing issue
Yeah, this is something that's just kind of
really stunning to me that
That there were so many warnings and that so many people tried to raise an alarm on this and that
so little action was taken and
Even this was last year
Zuckerberg finally said that Facebook would add
or maybe maybe this was actually this was probably two years ago said that Facebook would add but this is you know after
genocides already happening
Facebook would add dozens of Burmese language content reviewers
So in contrast
So we have this this is how Facebook really failed to respond in any any significant way in Myanmar
Germany passed a much stricter law about hate speech and nets
dgg
DC and
the
The potential penalty would be up to like 50 million euros
Facebook hired 1200 people in under a year because they were so worried about this penalty. And so
And I'm not saying like this is a law we want to replicate here. I'm just illustrating the difference between being told that you're
Contributing are playing a determining role in a genocide versus a significant
Financial penalty. We have seen what the one thing that makes Facebook take action is
and so I think that that is really significant in remembering what the what the power of a
Credible threat of a significant fine is and it has to be a lot more than you know, just like a cost of doing business
So I I really believe that we need both policy and
Ethical behavior within industry. I think that policy is the appropriate tool for addressing negative externalities
misaligned economic incentives race to the bottom situations and
enforcing accountability
however, ethical behavior of
Individuals and of data scientists and software engineers working in industry is very much necessary as well
Because the law is not always going to keep up. It's not going to cover all the edge cases
We really need the people in industry be making kind of ethical ethical decisions as well
And so I believe both are significant and important
And then and something to note here is that
Many many examples of kind of AI ethics issues and I haven't talked about all of these but there was
Amazon's facial recognition the ACLU did a study finding that it
correctly matched 28 members of Congress to criminal mug shots and this disproportionately included Congress people of color and
there's also
This was a terrible article. Not that the article was good, but the story is terrible of a
City that's using this IBM dashboard for predictive policing and a city official said, oh like whenever you have machine learning
it's always 99% accurate, which is
false
and quite concerning
We had we had the issue in so in 2016 Pro Publica discovered that
You could place a housing ad on Facebook and say you know
Like I don't want Latino or black people or I don't want wheelchair users to see this housing ad
which seems like a violation of the the Fair Housing Act and
So there's this article and Facebook was like we're so sorry and then over a year later
It was still going on ProPublica went back and wrote another article about it
There's also this issue of dozens of companies were
Placing ads on facebook job ads and saying like we only want young people to see this
There's the Amazon creating the recruiting tool that penalized
resumes that had the word Women's in that
and so something something to note about these examples and many of the examples we've
Talked about today is that many of these are about human rights and civil rights?
It's a good article by dominique harrison of the
Aspen Institute on this
And I kind of agree with an email - is framing I mean he wrote there is no technology industry anymore
Tech is being used in every industry. And so I think in particular
We need to consider
human rights and civil rights
such as housing education
employment criminal justice voting and medical care and think about what rights we we want a safeguard and I do think policy is
The appropriate way to do that
And I think I mean it's very easy to be discouraged about about regulation
But I think sometimes we overlook the the positive
Or the cases where where it's worked well
And so something I really liked about data sheets for data sets by - Nick Abreu at all. Is that
they go through three case studies of how
standardization and regular
Regulation came to different industries
And so it's the electronics industry around circuits and resistors
And so there that's kind of around the standardization of you know
what the specs are and what you write down about them and
The pharmaceutical industry and car safety and and none of these are perfect
But it's still it was a kind of very illuminating the the case studies there
I mean in particular I got very interested in the car safety one, and there's also a great
99% invisible episode. This is a design podcast about it. And so some some things I learned is that
Early cars had sharp metal knobs on the knobs on the dashboard that could Lodge in people's skulls in a crash
Non collapsible steering columns would frequently impale drivers and then even after the collapsible steering column was invented
It wasn't actually implemented because there was no economic incentive to do so
But it's the collapsible steering column has
This had saved more lives than anything other than the seatbelt when it comes to car safety
And there was also this just this widespread belief that cars were dangerous because of the people driving them and it took it took
Consumer safety advocates decades to just even change the culture of discussion around this and to start kind of gathering and tracking the data
and to put more of an onus on car companies
around safety
GM hired a private detective to
Trail Ralph Nader and try to dig up dirt on him
and so this was really a battle that we kind of I take for granted now and
and so
Kind of shows how much how much it can take to to change
Change the needle they are and then that kind of a more recent
Issue is that it wasn't until I believe
2011 that it was required that crash test dummies start representing the average female anatomy in addition to
Previously was kind of just crash test dummies or like men and that
in a crash with the same impact women were
40% more likely to be injured than men because that's kind of who the the cars were being designed for
So I thought I thought all this was very interesting and it can be helpful to kind of remember and remember some of the successes
we've had
and another area that's very relevant is
Environmental protections and kind of looking back and
May check the cloud ski has a great article on this but you know
just remembering like in the US we used to have rivers that would catch on fire and
London had terrible terrible smog and that these are things that were
You know very would not have been possible to kind of solve as an individual. We really needed kind of coordinated coordinated regulation on
All right, is then on a
Kind of closing note. So I think a lot of the problems I've touched fun tonight are really
huge
huge and difficult problems and they're often kind of very complicated and I
When I go into more detail on this in the course, so please please check out the course once it's once it's released
I always try to offer some like steps towards solutions, but I realize they're not they're not always
you know as satisfying as I would like of like this is gonna solve it and that's cuz these are really really difficult problems and
Julia Angwin a
former
Journalist from ProPublica and now the editor in chief of the mark-up
Gave a really great interview on privacy last year that I liked and found very encouraging
She said I strongly believe that in order to solve a problem
You have to diagnose it and that we're still in the dot the diagnosis phase of this
If you think about the turn of the entry and industrialization, we had I don't know 30 years of child labor
unlimited work hours terrible working conditions and it took a lot of journalists muckraking and
Advocacy to diagnose the problem and have some understanding of what it was and then the activism to get laws changed. I
See my role is trying to make as clear as possible what the downsides are and
Diagnosing them really accurately so that they can be solvable that's hard work and lots more people need to be doing it
Once I found that really encouraging and that I do I do think we should be working towards solutions
But I think just at this point even better diagnosing and understanding kind of the complex problems. We're facing is valuable work
Couple of people are very keen to see your full course on ethics. Is that something that they might be able to
Attend or buy or something. So it will be released for free at some point this summer
and it was there was a
paid in person version and offered at the data Institute as a certificate kind of
Similar to how this this course will was supposed to be offered, you know in person
The data ethics one was in person and that took place in January in February
and then I'm currently teaching a version version for the Masters of data science students at USF and I will be
releasing the free online version and yeah later
Sometime before July
Thank you. I will see you next time